Persico, Joseph; Papers apap030
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Joseph E. Persico Papers
1910-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap030
18.54 cubic ft. 4 films
The papers of Joseph Persico focus on his careers as a full-time author and as a political speechwriter for New York State Commissioner of Health, Hollis Ingraham, and New York State Governor, Nelson Rockefeller.
Biographical Sketch
Joseph E. Persico, author and former speechwriter for New York Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller, was born to Thomas and Blanche Persico of Gloversville, New York, on July 19, 1930. In 1952, after receiving a BA in both English and Political Science from the New York State College for Teachers (as the University at Albany was then known), he entered the U.S. Navy and remained in the military for three years. Persico served as a Lieutenant Junior Grade aboard a minesweeper and also with NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organization) Headquarters in Naples, Italy. Returning to the U.S. in 1956, Persico matriculated at Columbia University in New York for his graduate work.
In 1956, Joseph Persico began his political writing career, serving Governor W. Averell Harriman as a writer and researcher. After three years with Harriman, Persico then became a Foreign Service Officer for the United States Information Agency (USIA) working in Argentina, Brazil, and Washington. Between 1963 and 1966, Persico served as Executive Assistant to the New York State Health Commissioner, Hollis Ingraham. In 1966, Joseph Persico became the chief speechwriter for New York Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller. Continuing in this position for seven years, he remained Rockefeller's primary speechwriter as the Governor assumed the office of Vice President of the United States from 1974 to 1977.
In 1977, Joseph Persico transitioned into a full-time author, focusing on historical subjects. In that year, his Civil War piece, My Enemy My Brother: Men and Days of Gettysburg, was released. Two years later, he followed up this work with a novel, The Spiderweb, and a nonfiction study, Piercing the Reich: The Penetration of Nazi Germany by American Secret Agents During World War II. In 1982, Persico focused on Nelson Rockefeller's life and published the biography, The Imperial Rockefeller. During the 1990s, Persico created other historical works on both American espionage and the Nuremberg War Crimes Trials following World War II. These works were Casey: From the OSS to the CIA and Nuremberg: Infamy on Trial. Persico also targeted renowned broadcast journalist Edward R. Murrow for a biographical sketch in 1990. In addition to his books, Persico has also published numerous articles on American history.
Persico collaborated with former Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and later Secretary of State, Colin L. Powell, on his biography. Between 1994 and 1996, the author developed a personal relationship with his subject, occasionally addressing Powell as "Sir Colin", and "Mon General", from "The Hired Pen". Joseph Persico continues to publish books on historical subjects. In November 2001, Random House Inc. released Roosevelt's Secret War: FDR and World War II Espionage and in 2004, Eleventh Month, Eleventh Day, Eleventh Hour: Armistice Day, 1918, World War I and Its Violent Climax was published.
Apart from his professional career, Joseph Persico's private life has been spent with his wife, Sylvia La Vista Persico, and his children, Vanya and Andrea. He currently lives in Guilderland, N.Y.
Chronological Index to Press Releases, Speeches, and Transcripts Written for Nelson A. Rockefeller
This index was transcribed from the handwritten original provided by the donor covering the years 1964-1976.
Scope and Contents
The collected papers of Joseph Persico focus on his careers as a political speechwriter and as a full-time author. His speeches from the 1960s include his work for both New York State Commissioner of Health, Hollis Ingraham, and New York State Governor, Nelson Rockefeller. Press releases and transcripts associated with the speeches are also present in the Persico files. Nelson Rockefeller's Messages to the Legislature and "Quotes on Issues" during the late 1960s and early 1970s have been filed in Series 1 with Persico's speeches. The Chronological Index to Press Releases, Speeches, and Transcripts Written for Nelson A. Rockefeller was transcribed by Kevin Lawyer from the handwritten original provided by the donor. The index covers the years 1964-1976.
The author's publications files include manuscripts, correspondence, screenplays, interviews for The Imperial Rockefeller, and research notes. For Persico's Piercing the Reich, several folders hold parts of a single OSS (Office of Strategic Services) War Report from 1949, detailing OSS action in Europe, Africa, and Asia during World War II. For Nuremberg: Infamy on Trial, the author's files contain a draft of the work and research material including photos from the Holocaust and the Nuremberg Trials.
The texts, drafts, news clippings, correspondence, and other supporting material is available for speeches and other non-book writings of Persico. Among the author's correspondence is an exchange with movie director John Huston who Persico interviewed for an article in American Heritage. Note that correspondence can be found throughout the collection. For example, references to Persico's publications will be found in both the general correspondence files and specific publications' series. An attempt was made to retain the original filing system of the creator with the most recent accessions, but previous arrangement divided some of the correspondence into professional and personal folders.
The material received from the donor in 2006, 2012-2013, and 2018 is not yet arranged and described in this finding aid. Contact Department staff for further information.
Additional material collected and created by Persico during the writing of Piercing the Reich was deposited by Persico at the Hoover Institution Library and Archives at Stanford University. The finding aid for this material is available online through the Online Archive of California. Persico also gave additional material related to his book Edward R. Murrow: An American Original to the Edward R. Murrow Center of Public Diplomacy at Tufts University.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into five series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Joseph E. Persico in 1984. The Department received additional material from Mr. Persico in August 1997, May 1998, December 1999, December 2003, May 2006, October 2012, July 2013, and April 2018.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Selected Bibliography
My Enemy, My Brother: Men and Days of Gettsburg. New York: Viking Press, 1977.
Piercing the Reich: The Penetration of Nazi Germany by American Secret Agents during World War II. New York: Viking Press, 1979.
The Spiderweb, 1981
The Imperial Rockefeller: A Biography of Nelson A. Rockefeller. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1982.
Edward R. Murrow: An American Original. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1988.
Casey: From the OSS to the CIA. New York: Viking, 1990.
Nuremberg: Infamy on Trial. New York: Viking, 1994.
My American Journey. New York, NY: Random House, 1995. Co-authored with Colin Powell.
Roosevelt's Secret War: FDR and World War II Espionage. New York: Random House, 2001.
Eleventh Month, Eleventh Day, Eleventh Hour: Armistice Day, 1918, World War I and Its Violent Climax. New York, NY: Random House, 2004.
Women; State University of New York SUNY, Central Administration; Public Servants; Military and Armed Conflict; Medicine and Health Care; Education; Albany, New York; Generals -- United States.; Gettysburg Campaign, 1863.; Government and the press -- New York (State); Intelligence officers -- United States.; Nuremberg Trial of Major German War Criminals, Nuremberg, Germany, 1945-1946.; New York (State) -- Politics and government.; United States -- Politics and government.; Casey, William J.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Murrow, Edward R.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; United States. Office of Strategic Services.
- New York State Government Career, 1910-1981; 1; 9.8 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Persico's public papers, including press releases, transcripts of press conferences, television and radio interviews, and drafts of speeches written for New York State Commissioner of Health Hollis Ingraham and Nelson A. Rockefeller (1964-1977). Press releases and transcripts associated with the speeches are also present in the Persico files. Rockefeller's Messages to the Legislature and "Quotes on Issues" during the late 1960s and early 1970s have been filed in this series with the speeches written by Persico. Several boxes contained in this series are subject files relating personally to the author, his work, and to Nelson Rockefeller. A partial index to speeches is available in the Department of Special Collections and Archives. Consult a staff member for details. Also included in this series are subject files and news clippings. While most of these documents date from 1964-1977, some related materials date from 1947-1981.
  The Chronological Index to Press Releases, Speeches, and Transcripts Written for Nelson A. Rockefeller was transcribed by Kevin Lawyer from the handwritten original provided by the donor. The index covers the years 1964-1976.
  - Speeches, Press Releases, and Transcripts, 1965-1976; 1.1
    - Persico's Notepads, ca. 1966-1974 (Box 1 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1A)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1964 July-1965 October (Box 1 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1966 January-1966 September (Box 1 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1966 October-1966 November (Box 1 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1968 January-1968 March (Box 1 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1968 April-1968 June (Box 1 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1968 July-1968 December (Box 1 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1969 January-1969 May (Box 1A (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1969 June-1969 December (Box 1A (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 January-1970 February (Box 2 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 March (Box 2 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 March (Box 2 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 April (Box 2 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 April (Box 2 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 May (Box 3 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 May (Box 3 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 June (Box 3 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 June (Box 3 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 July (Box 3 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 August (Box 4 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 August (Box 4 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 September (Box 4 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 September (Box 4 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 October (Box 4 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 October (Box 5 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1970 November (Box 5 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, 1970 December (Box 5 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, 1970 December (Box 5 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, 1970 December (Box 5 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 January (Box 5 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, 1971 February (Box 5 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 March (Box 6 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 April (Box 6 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 May (Box 6 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 June (Box 6 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 July (Box 6 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 August (Box 6 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 September (Box 6 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 October (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 November (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1971 December (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 January (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 February (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 March (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 April (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 May (Box 7 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 8)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 June (Box 8 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 July (Box 8 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 August (Box 8 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 September (Box 8 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 October (Box 8 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 November (Box 8 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 November (Box 8 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, 1972 November (Box 9 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 November (Box 9 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 November (Box 9 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, 1972 November (Box 9 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1972 December (Box 9 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 January (Box 9 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 January (Box 10 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, 1973 February (Box 10 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 March (Box 10 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 April (Box 10 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 May (Box 10 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 June (Box 10 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 July (Box 10 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 August (Box 11 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 September (Box 11 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 September (Box 11 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 October (Box 11 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 October (Box 11 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 November (Box 11 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1973 December (Box 12 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1974 January (Box 12 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1974 February (Box 12 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1974 February (Box 12 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1974 March (Box 12 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1974 March (Box 12 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, 1974 April (Box 12 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1974 May (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches and Transcripts, 1974 June (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches and Transcripts, 1974 July (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches and Transcripts, 1974 August (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1974 September (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches and Transcripts, 1974 October (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 January (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 February-1975 May (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 8)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 June-1975 August (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 9)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 September (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 10)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 October (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 11)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 October (Box 13 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 12)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 November (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1975 December (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 January (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 February (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 March (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 April (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 May (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 June (Box 14 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 8)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 July (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 August (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 September (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 September (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 October (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 October (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 November (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speeches, Press Releases and Transcripts, 1976 December (Box 15 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 8)
    - Messages to Legislature, 1967-1974 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Speech Index, 1966 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Speech Index, 1967 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Speech Index, 1968 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Speech Index, 1969 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Speech Index, 1970 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Speech Index, 1971 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)
    - Speech Index, 1972 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 8)
    - Speech Index, 1973 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 9)
    - Speech Index, 1974 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 10)
    - Speech Index, 1975-1976 (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 11)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller's (NAR) Quotes on Issues, (used through 1973) (Box 16 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 12)
    - Letters, 1970-1976 (Box 17 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1-3)
    - Memos, 1967-1971 (Box 17 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4-10)
    - Memos, 1972-1976; Undated (Box 17A (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1-6)
  - Subject Files, 1947-1976; 1.2
    - Subject File Listings (Composition Notebook), 1970s (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1A)
    - Abortion, 1970-1974 (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 1)
    - Acupuncture, 1972-1974 (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 2)
    - Admiral's House, 1975 (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 3)
    - Adirondack State Park, 1973-1975 (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 4)
    - Agriculture, 1970-1973 (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 5)
    - Administration, 1974-1977 (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 6)
    - Arts, 1969-1974 (Box 18 (1-New York State Government Career), Folder 7)